Leah: Let’s look at Media
influences in a little more detail.
Mental health and mental ill health
are commonly portrayed in the media
both negatively and positively.
This can be through news articles
both on TV and in newspapers, in films
and tv programmes both fictional and
non-fictional, on children's TV and
also across digital and social media.
Rhiannon: If mental health is shown
as a good news story with positive
endorsements, for example, fund raising
success, support and feel-good factors
such as ‘comic relief’, this will
influence people in a positive way and
they will remember the good things.
Leah: If mental health is shown negatively
such as showing violence and bad
behaviour in a news article, documentary
or a storyline for a drama, this will
have negative influences on attitudes.
Rhiannon: However, some media reporting,
even though the content shows negative
things, can have a positive effect
as it raises everyone’s awareness.
Such as cases of abuse for
example, child neglect, human
trafficking, child endangerment
and child sexual exploitation.
Leah: By this being shown widely
in the media, it can help encourage
more people to come forward with
information and make more of the public
open to discussion of these topics,
ultimately raising the profile of
mental health issues as a consequence.
Rhiannon: Journalists, script writers
and other media professionals have to
ensure fictional and factual portrayals
of people with mental health problems
in the media are accurate and sensitive.
Leah: More and more ‘bloggers'
and ‘vloggers' are now responding
to these portrayals, relaying
their own experiences and raising
awareness of the different attitudes
they have personally encountered.
Rhiannon: Digital and social media
is a big part of most young peoples
lives and they can gain a lot of
positivity from what is out there,
however there is also a lot of
negativity carried in these formats too.
Leah: If what children and young
people see online and how mental health
issues are portrayed only leaves them
angry, sad, worried, stressed, or
annoyed, this can build up and start
having a negative impact on their
life and their own mental health.
Rhiannon: For example, they may
start worrying more about how they
look or what they’re missing out on.
A lot of people maintain an overly
idealised online presence or world, which
many others then fail to see as such,
instead struggling to keep a positive
view of their own lives by contrast.
Leah: We cannot ignore the media
as individuals are continuously
consuming its output however we need
to be aware that the way things are
represented need to be realistic or for
a specific storyline and not used in
a derogatory or flippant manner just
to make good TV or for sensationalism.
Rhiannon: Mental health needs to be shown
appropriately and should be relevant
if society is to become more accepting.